<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[VaccineKeeper kids]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-06T17:10:28-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Janiak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[This app will fulfill all your vaccination scheduling needs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2014/02/06/this-app-will-fulfill-all-your-vaccination-scheduling-needs/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T16:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2014/02/06/this-app-will-fulfill-all-your-vaccination-scheduling-needs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It only took a year but Vaccine Keeper <em>kids</em> is finally ready to take on users!</p>

<p>Right now, Vaccine Keeper <em>kids</em> is a web app but it will format itself to mobile phones or tables.
This enables us to quickly implement changes from user feedback to make the app as effective and user friendly as possible.</p>

<p>Gradually once you are happy with the app we will port Vaccine Keeper <em>kids</em> onto iOS and Android platforms.</p>

<p>Feel free to <a href="www.vaccinekeeper.com/signup">sign up</a> and you will receive an email with your login details.
I suggest that you sign up with a Google email and login by pressing the Google login button
so that Vaccine Keeper can set reminders on your Google calendar.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prospective HIV/AIDS vaccine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2013/11/01/prospective-hiv-slash-aids-vaccine/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2013/11/01/prospective-hiv-slash-aids-vaccine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After years of trying and <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/04/26/179231916/failure-of-latest-hiv-vaccine-test-a-huge-disappointment">numerous failed attempts</a>
there finally appears to be some hope for the prevention or curing of HIV.</p>

<p>Early in the year, scientists appear to have <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/03/health/hiv-toddler-cured/">cured a toddler born with HIV</a>.
In September, scientists located a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/17/science/new-hope-for-hiv-vaccine.html">worthy HIV vaccine candidate</a>.
And most recently, scientists succeeded in <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/10419278/HIV-vaccine-possible-after-scientific-breakthrough-study-claims.html">mapping HIV&rsquo;s envelope protein</a>
, which is a critical step to understanding and modelling how the virus evades our immune system.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why is it so?</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="https://pubs.acs.org/cen/_img/86/i38/8638cov1_live-4.gif" width="275" height="310" title="'HIV structure'" >
All this reading got me thinking about why it&rsquo;s so hard to prevent / cure HIV. I always thought it had something to do with how HIV is a retrovirus,
which meant that it could evade our immune response, but when I researched further, as you&rsquo;d expect there&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.aidsmap.com/Why-is-it-so-hard-to-make-a-vaccine-against-HIV/page/1271042/">a lot more to it</a>.</p>

<p>Firstly, creating vaccines was never easy&hellip; Typhoid, whooping cough, polio, measles, all these vaccines took 40+
years to develop after the discovery of the relative bacterium or virus. With HIV we&rsquo;re hitting on 30 years, AIDS was first clinically observed in the US in 1981.</p>

<p>Secondly, HIV is sneaky. The fact that it&rsquo;s a retro virus is a key factor, this means that the virus can integrate with our DNA and become invisible
to our immune system. So if you are to prevent HIV, you need to catch it at the very onset of infection, before it has had a chance to integrate.
But let&rsquo;s say that you do find a vaccine or treatment, the virus is still <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/09/120913123524.htm">likely to mutate</a>,
meaning that you&rsquo;ll probably need regular boosters like with the flu vaccine.</p>

<p>There is also a plethora of other factors. Tried and tested techniques for creating a vaccine don&rsquo;t work, killed whole viruses or attenuated viruses
provide a risk of reactivation or are simply ineffective. You cannot test HIV on monkeys because the simian sersion of the virus does not have the
same effects on the immune system as the human version. As mentioned above, until recently, using technology to model the virus&#8217; behavior
has also proven difficult. What this boils down to is even if we could get around HIV&rsquo;s sneakiness, we still don&rsquo;t know which immune response to trigger
so that our immune system will dispatch it.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s next?</h2>

<p>Based on our track record, it looks like we have at least another 10 years to go before we have an effective HIV vaccine.
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pre-exposure_prophylaxis">Pre-exposure prophylaxis</a> trials have effectiveness rates of 40 to 70% but there&rsquo;s still
a way to go before we reach 100%.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile, my dad always said that an ounce of prevention is better than a ton of cure. I never understood why he used imperial units in metric country
but the general sentiment is correct. The CDC still recommends the <a href="http://www.cdcnpin.org/scripts/hiv/prevent.asp">common sense methods of HIV prevention </a>,
which could be summarized by saying: be sensible and stay out of trouble!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress with Github Pages and Cloud9]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2013/08/22/octopress-with-github-pages-and-cloud9/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-22T14:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.vaccinekeeper.com/blog/2013/08/22/octopress-with-github-pages-and-cloud9</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog runs on <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>, a framework for <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>
and is hosted on <a href="http://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a>. I&rsquo;ve also set it up on <a href="https://c9.io/">Cloud9</a>, a
useful web IDE that enables you to write blog posts on any device.</p>

<p>Having done a bit of research, when it comes down to blogging solutions, you either have php based CMS&rsquo;s
such as <a href="http://wordpress.org/">WordPress</a>, Drupal, Joomla or static site generators like Jekyll. I&rsquo;ve used Wordpress before
but it&rsquo;s functionality has always irritated me, probably because my php is awful, it&rsquo;s too bloated for what I need
and don&rsquo;t want to use a database for various reasons.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Jekyll has all the functionality I need from a blog but without a database, which
means I can host it from a static hosting service like GitHub Pages or <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">Amazon S3</a>.
Not only are these services more or less free but they should be more robust than your random
shared web hosting provider.</p>

<p>Jekyll by itself is bare bones, you need to create your own directory structure, templates etc, so to make life
easier I turned to Octopress, an establish framework that takes care of some pain.</p>

<p>The only thing missing with Octopress / Jekyll is it doesn&rsquo;t have a web interface for when I&rsquo;m on the go,
so that&rsquo;s why I plugged it into Cloud9. In addition to an IDE, Cloud9 provides a
Ruby virtual machine. Jekyll runs on Ruby, so this means I can do 100% of the setup from Cloud9. Win.</p>

<p>Getting it running wasn&rsquo;t completely trivial so I figure this could be a useful blog post for those that are into this kind of thing.</p>

<hr/>


<h4>0. Open a GitHub account and set up a public SSH key that you can use with Cloud9</h4>

<p>Out of scope for this blog but there are plenty of instructions floating around on the web,
including those <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/generating-ssh-keys">straight from the horses mouth</a>.</p>

<hr/>


<h4>1. Create a repository for the GitHub Pages hosted website</h4>

<p>Decide on an <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/user-organization-and-project-pages">organization or project page</a>. I went with an organization page,
so if you want to set that up on your GitHub account go to the GitHub
<a href="https://github.com/account/organizations/new">new organization page</a>.</p>

<p>Create a repository for your website. The naming convention is important, it must be <code>organization.github.io</code> or <code>user.github.io</code>.
I&rsquo;ve seen <code>.com</code> work too. So <code>organization.github.io</code> will output a website at: <code>http://organization.github.io</code>.
No need to create a README or put anything in the repository for now.</p>

<hr/>


<h4>2. Open a Cloud9 account and create a workspace with Octopress on it</h4>

<p>Go to <a href="c9.io">Cloud9</a> and login with your github account. Click on the &ldquo;Create new workspace&rdquo; button, then select &ldquo;clone from URL&rdquo;.
Use the following url <code>git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git</code> and name it whatever you want.</p>

<hr/>


<h4>3. Set Octopress up within Cloud9</h4>

<p>Click on your Octopress project and hit the &ldquo;start editing&rdquo; button. You don&rsquo;t really need to do this but you can check
the ruby version just in case, it should be 1.9.3.</p>

<pre><code>ruby --version
</code></pre>

<p>install the bundler dependency manager</p>

<pre><code>gem install bundler
</code></pre>

<p>install dependencies specified in Gemfile</p>

<pre><code>bundle install
</code></pre>

<p>Octopress has its own Ruby <a href="http://rake.rubyforge.org/doc/rakefile_rdoc.html">Rakefile</a> with a whole bunch of extremely useful tasks.
It&rsquo;s pretty awesome, just type <code>rake -T</code> into the terminal to see a list of commands.</p>

<p>First up, install the default theme</p>

<pre><code>rake install
</code></pre>

<hr/>


<h4>4. At this stage you can generate your blog and view a preview or you can go straight to 5</h4>

<p>Unlike Wordpress, which actively pulls your posts out of a database, Jekyll parses your source files then uses that information
to generate a static version of your website. Every time you make a change to the source, that is write a new page or blog post,
you need to generate a new blog. <a href="http://jekyllbootstrap.com/lessons/jekyll-introduction.html">More here</a>.</p>

<p>Run the Octopress blog generator</p>

<pre><code>rake generate
</code></pre>

<p>If you run the preview now you will get <code>Error: you may be using the wrong PORT &amp; HOST for your server app</code></p>

<p>To fix that, <a href="http://www.devopsy.com/blog/2012/10/04/octopress-on-cloud9/">edit the Rakefile</a>:</p>

<pre><code># server_port     = "4000"      # Find this line and replace it with the lines below
server_host     = ENV['IP'] ||= '0.0.0.0' # server bind address for preview server
server_port     = ENV['PORT'] ||= "4000"  # port for preview server eg. localhost:4000
# rackupPid = Process.spawn("rackup --port #{server_port}")
rackupPid = Process.spawn("rackup --host #{server_host} --port #{server_port}")
</code></pre>

<p>New you can view a preview at <code>http://workspace.accountname.c9.io</code> just type</p>

<pre><code>rake preview
</code></pre>

<hr/>


<h4>5. Get your blog ready for GitHub pages</h4>

<p>Octopress gives you a single command for setting up on GitHub pages that does lots of useful things,
<a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github">read more here</a></p>

<pre><code>rake setup_github_pages
</code></pre>

<p>You will need to enter your repository url <code>git@github.com:organization/organization.github.io.git</code></p>

<p>Your source is now on your &ldquo;source&rdquo; branch, while your blog is on the &ldquo;master&rdquo; branch</p>

<hr/>


<h4>6. Deploy and commit everything to GitHub</h4>

<p>Generate your blog content (if you skipped step 4)</p>

<pre><code>rake generate
</code></pre>

<p>Deploy the master branch, that is the static assets for your blog onto GitHub using Octopress&#8217; deploy command</p>

<pre><code>rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>Commit the source branch to GitHub</p>

<pre><code>git add .
git commit -m 'source commit'
git push origin source
</code></pre>

<p>Now if you go to your repository at <code>github.com/organization/organization.github.io</code> you will notice that
you have two branches, a master branch and a source and if you go to <code>http://organization.github.io/</code>
you have your blog!</p>

<hr/>


<h4>7. Start <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/blogging/">blogging with Octopress</a></h4>

<pre><code>rake new_post["Octopress rulez"]
rake generate
</code></pre>

<p>then preview or deploy</p>

<pre><code>rake preview
rake deploy
</code></pre>

<p>And remember to commit the source</p>

<pre><code>git add .
git commit -m 'source commit'
git push origin source
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
