<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vaccines | VaccineKeeper]]></title>
  <link href="http://vaccinekeeper.github.io/blog/categories/vaccines/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vaccinekeeper.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-01T14:01:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vaccinekeeper.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Janiak]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prospective HIV/AIDS vaccine]]></title>
    <link href="http://vaccinekeeper.github.io/blog/2013/11/01/prospective-hiv-slash-aids-vaccine/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T12:06:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vaccinekeeper.github.io/blog/2013/11/01/prospective-hiv-slash-aids-vaccine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After years of trying and <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/health/2013/04/26/179231916/failure-of-latest-hiv-vaccine-test-a-huge-disappointment">numerous failed attempts</a>
there finally appears to be some hope for the prevention or curing of HIV/AIDS.</p>

<p>Earlier in the year, scientists appear to have <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2013/03/03/health/hiv-toddler-cured/">cured a toddler born with HIV</a>.
Back in September, scientists located a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/17/science/new-hope-for-hiv-vaccine.html">worthy HIV vaccine candidate</a>.
And most recently scientists succeeded in <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/healthnews/10419278/HIV-vaccine-possible-after-scientific-breakthrough-study-claims.html">mapping HIV&rsquo;s envelope protein</a>
, which is a critical step to understanding and modelling how the virus gets around our immune system.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why is it so?</h2>

<p><img class="left <a" src="href="https://pubs.acs.org/cen/_img/86/i38/8638cov1_live-4.gif">https://pubs.acs.org/cen/_img/86/i38/8638cov1_live-4.gif</a>" width="275" height="310" title="&lsquo;HIV structure&rsquo;" >
All this reading got me thinking about why it&rsquo;s so hard to prevent / cure HIV. I always thought it had something to do with how HIV is a retrovirus,
which meant that it could evade our immune response, but when I dug into it, it turns out that there is <a href="http://www.aidsmap.com/Why-is-it-so-hard-to-make-a-vaccine-against-HIV/page/1271042/">a lot more to it</a>.</p>

<p>Firstly, it was never easy finding vaccines for diseases in the first place&hellip; Typhoid, whooping cough, polio, measles, all these vaccines took 40+
years to develop after the discovery of the relative bacterium or virus. With HIV we&rsquo;re hitting on 30 years, AIDS was first clinically observed in the US in 1981.</p>

<p>Secondly, HIV is sneaky. The fact that its a retro virus has a lot to do with it, this means that the virus can integrate with our DNA and become invisible
to our immune system. So if you are to prevent HIV, you need to catch it at the very onset of infection, before it has had a chance to become invisible.
But let&rsquo;s say that you find some kind of vaccine or treatment, the virus is still <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/09/120913123524.htm">likely to mutate</a>,
meaning that you&rsquo;ll probably need regular boosters like with the flu vaccine.</p>

<p>There is also a plethora of other factors. Tried and tested techniques for creating a vaccine don&rsquo;t work, killed whole viruses or attenuated viruses
provide a risk of reactivation or are simply ineffective. You cannot test HIV on monkeys because the simian sersion of the virus does not have the
same effects on the immune system as the human version. As mentioned above, until recently, using technology to model the virus' behavior
has also proven difficult. What this boils down to is even if we could get around HIV&rsquo;s sneakiness, we still don&rsquo;t know which immune response to trigger
so that our immune system will dispatch it.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s next?</h2>

<p>Based on our track record, it looks like we have at least another 10 years to go before we have an effective HIV vaccine.
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pre-exposure_prophylaxis">Pre-exposure prophylaxis</a> trials have effectiveness rates of 40 to 70% but there&rsquo;s still
a way to go before we reach 100%.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile, my dad always said that an ounce of prevention is better than a ton of cure. I don&rsquo;t know why he used imperial units in metric country
but the general sentiment is correct. The CDC still recommends the <a href="http://www.cdcnpin.org/scripts/hiv/prevent.asp">common sense methods of HIV prevention </a>,
which could be summarized by saying: be sensible and stay out of trouble!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
